Good morning everybody. Shh. Quiet, please. Quiet, please. Good morning. Okay, today's
דף Daf is נ'. Nun. We pick up in the middle of
מ"ט עמוד ב'. Mem Tet Amud Bet. We are dealing with the
issue of the father's obligation to feed his children. The משנה Mishnah
said there's no obligation to feed the daughter. The גמרא Gemara continued
by saying also no obligation to feed the sons. Question, which is
the one that I might have expected more of an obligation towards.
Certainly I would say the פשט Pshat of the משנה Mishnah seems
to follow רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says there should be in
principle more of an obligation towards the daughters because the daughters are
the ones that can less provide for themselves in that type of
a society. Nevertheless, the משנה Mishnah said there's no obligation to feed
either. However, there's a מצוה Mitzvah to feed one's children. There's a
religious, moral imperative but nothing that can actually be sort of, you
know, enforced by the court and we're about to see how that
played out. Before we get to seeing how it played out, if
you take a look at the tiny little תוספות Tosafos on the
top of מ"ט עמוד ב', Mem Tet Amud Bet, לשם קטנים, L'shem
Kitanim, תוספות Tosafos
says אבל קטני קטנים לכולי עלמא חייב Aval kitanei kitanim l'chulei alma
chayav כדאמר בסוף אף על פי. kid'amar besof af al pi. So
we'll be seeing a little bit later that when they're really in
their infant stage there is an obligation, but once they are a
few years old, we'll see exactly how old, but anyway, then there
is not. So now the question is going to be okay, but
it's certainly socially expected and morally and religiously understood. But what happens
if somebody is not doing it? So let's take a look as
we continue in the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this... okay...
אמר רבי אילא אמר ריש לקיש. Amar Rabbi Ila Amar Reish Lakish.
Line starts with the word ריש לקיש Reish Lakish about 10 lines
down. משום רבי יהודה בר חנינא. Mishum Rabbi Yehuda Bar Chanina. באושא
התקינו, Be-Usha Hitkinu, in אושא, Usha, which is where the סנהדרין Sanhedrin
moved after the חורבן הבית. Churban Habayit. So there and there was
a whole series of תקנות Takanot that they made in אושא Usha
and actually what we're going to be seeing on today's דף Daf
is a list of various
תקנות Takanot that were established in אושא, Usha, not really related to
one another. So in
אושא, Usha, actually I'm sorry רש"י Rashi says that אושא Usha was,
excuse me my mistake, is where the סנהדרין Sanhedrin moved before חורבן
הבית. Churban Habayit. If you look at רש"י Rashi three lines from
the top, באושא התקינו, Be-Usha Hitkinu, כשיישבו סנהדרי גדולה באושא שהיא אחת
מעשר גליות שגלתה סנהדרין כדאמר בראש השנה. keshe-yashvu Sanhedrei Gedolah Be-Usha, shehi
achas m'eser galuyot she-galta Sanhedrin k'd'amar be-Rosh Hashanah.
So this was actually before חורבן הבית Churban Habayit but as the
situation was getting worse and worse and there was a sense that
the סנהדרין Sanhedrin had, the same way sort of paralleling to the
idea that the שכינה Shechinah was slowly removing itself from הר הבית,
Har Habayit, the סנהדרין Sanhedrin was removing itself as well. Anyway, in
this period right leading up to the חורבן הבית, Churban Habayit, when
the סנהדרין Sanhedrin was in אושא, Usha, they made the following תקנה.
Takana. So let's take a look. באושא התקינו Be-Usha Hitkinu שהאדם, she-adam,
so this רבי יהודה בר חנינא Rabbi Yehuda Bar Chanina says, אמר
רבי אילא Amar Rabbi Ila in the name of ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish in the name of רבי יהודה בר חנינא, Rabbi Yehuda Bar
Chanina, באושא התקינו שהאדם זן את בניו ואת בנותיו כשהן קטנים. Be-Usha
Hitkinu she-adam zan et banav v'et benotav k'shehen ketanim. That a person
should שיהא, sheyehei, interesting, like obligated let's say or must feed his
children while they are still small, daughters and sons and daughters. So
איבעיא להו, Iba'ya Lehu, הלכתא כוותיה או אין הלכתא כוותיה. hilchata kevataih
o ein hilchata kevataih. Do we rule that way or not? Which
is pretty funny because normally all the תקנות Takanot of אושא Usha
are normally generally like assumed that, okay, there's a הלכה. Halacha. I
mean that was the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, that was a תקנה. Takana. But
let's take a look, the גמרא Gemara presumably understood that this one
was not so necessarily universally accepted or embraced. So איבעיא להו, Iba'ya
Lehu, הלכתא כוותיה או אין הלכתא כוותיה. hilchata kevataih o ein hilchata
kevataih. תא שמע, Ta Shema, come hear. כי הוה אתי לקמיה דרבי
יהודה, Ki hava atei l'kamei d'Rabbi Yehuda, when they, meaning like young
children or whatever would come to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and say
that they demanded to be fed and their father wasn't feeding them,
so אמר להו, amar lehu, ירוד ילדה ואבני מתא שדיא? yarod yalada
v'avnei mata shadya? Would a serpent, a snake, you know, give birth,
only a snake basically, let me put it that way, only a
snake gives birth and throws their
responsibility onto the city?
So, or actually I'm sorry רש"י Rashi says this, פטמיא, pitmya, I
think רש"י Rashi says, no, okay I keep on reversing myself, התנין
הוליד תולדותיו והיטל על בני העיר, hatnin holid toldotav v'hital banai ha'ir,
right.
So it's only the cruel type of a creature, you know, of
the animals, only the cruelest animal would have children and not take
responsibility for them and put that responsibility on others. So like being
like a snake or serpent that you go ahead and have kids
and you don't feed them. Of course the גמרא Gemara says that
this proves that they did not rule like אושא Usha because the
fact that they had to shame the person and try to persuade
him rather than actually saying, okay you're חייב chayav to feed your
kids, shows that they did not rule like
אושא. Usha. They just did the opposite. Rhetorical. Of course you would
never think that. No, they were being brought as a court case
and they were suing for whatever and this was his response. Response
wasn't חייב, chayav, his response was you're acting like a snake. So
let's take a look. איבעיא להו. Iba'ya Lehu. So,
when they would come to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, אמר להו amar
lehu he would say, כפו ליה אציתא בציבורא, kofu lei asita b'tzibora,
turn up
sort of overturn for him regarding him the father a like a...
a mortar in the marketplace, like stand on a soapbox essentially is
the image, וליקו ולימא v'leiku v'leima stand on it and proclaim, עורבא
בעי בני orva bei b'nei
even a raven is concerned for his children, וההוא גברא לא בעי
בני v'hahu gavra lo bei b'nei and this person has no concern
for his children that he lets them starve to death and he
won't pay for their food. So
רש"י, Rashi, by the way, says that there's a question whether who's
saying this. Are you forcing the man himself to say it about
himself, a raven feeds his children and I won't feed my children,
or is somebody sort of
a public crier the one that's standing up and making this proclamation?
But either way, the point is you're taking out an ad in
the newspaper and you're saying the following deadbeat fathers won't support their
children, but you're not actually legally obligating them. So you're shaming them,
but they're not actually legally obligated. Doesn't it seem like though that
we say shaming is social pressure, right? So even though it may
not be the letter of the law or the core of the
law, but there's some more kind of formal way to deal with
this as merging these stories that it sounds like the people's expression
of frustration that they can't do anything else, so they shout it
out in the marketplace rather than following a procedure which is established.
Which is I think exactly the point though is that they understood
that they were not empowered to legally do anything, so then what
they're left with is just a sense of like social censure. But
you're right, you do get this undertone of frustration. But you mean
if your question is like why not, why did they not just
adopt the תקנת אושא takanat Usha or whatever? Yeah, I don't know,
it's an interesting question. I mean, normally we assume it's a תקנת
אושא takanat Usha they should have adopted it in a way which
it would seem like it would be easier. You know, you have
a whole apparatus, a court apparatus, just go ahead and make the
guy pay. You know, why also have to- this
is like what we do nowadays sometimes because of the עגונה aguna
situation. We feel okay, so we don't have any like legal recourse,
we're going to try to shame the person. Yeah, but like why-
so I can't explain why the assumption was was that they did
not rule like אושא. Usha.
But nevertheless, Charlie, you wanted to say something? I was going to
say ravens actually typically are mated pairs, so most ravens. But other
animals generally aren't.
You mean in terms of abandoning their kids? Well, that's the גמרא's
Gemara next line. Let's read the next line. The גמרא Gemara says
like this: עורבא בעי בני? orva bei b'nei? Oh no, actually the
opposite, I'm sorry, because the גמרא Gemara had said that a raven
does take care of the children and you won't. So the גמרא
Gemara says: ועורבא בעי בני? v'orva bei b'nei? Does a raven really
take care of the children? והכתיב לבני עורב אשר יקראו v'haksiv livnei
oreiv asher yikra'u that God takes care of the children of the
raven that call out to God,
which basically means that the raven isn't taking care of its own
kids. So the גמרא Gemara says how come you say that I'm
worse than a raven? So the גמרא Gemara says: לא קשיא. lo
kashya. הא בחיורי הא באוכמי. ha b'chiveri ha b'uchmi. There are different
species of ravens, the white and the dark black ones. So some-
right, whatever, some of them the ravens take care of their kids,
some of them they don't. רש"י Rashi says that it also might-
תוספות Tosafot says it's different species. תוספות Tosafot says it's the ages.
When ravens are just born, רש"י Rashi says they're white, I have
no idea if that's true. Anyway, he says, and then the ravens
don't care for them because then they don't look like- they don't
look like ravens. It's only when they start getting black in their
feathers or something that then they start paying attention to their kids.
Yes. I was going to say though, you also have the example
of בן סורר
ומורה ben soreir u'moreh that you know, that the בית דין Beit
Din is empowered to do something and they hang the guy. So
like you know, let it be- you know- not so you got-
I don't understand that. Bringing this back into the cases before, not
only is בית דין Beit Din empowered, but this is such a
bad thing we want to make an example of this guy. Let-
let no one ever think that בית דין Beit Din isn't going
to take care of these people. בית דין Beit Din is empowered
and anyone who's going to go against this, we're going to publicly
shame you. Yeah,
okay, fine, you're constructing a whole thing. בן סורר ומורה ben soreir
u'moreh is a case in the תורה. Torah. I mean, the גמרא,
Gemara, you know, what can I tell you? The גמרא Gemara understood
that the reality was not that way, the reality was that this
was their only recourse. I guess how do you go against a
תקנה takana then? Alright, so that I don't know. So I mean
you could say אין מעיינין במילי דאגדתא ein me'aynin b'milei d'agadata or
whatever, which is pretty interesting because- okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this: כי הוו אתו לקמיה דרבא ki havu asu lakamei
d'Rava when they came to רבא, Rava, אמר ליה amar lei
he said, ניחא לך דמיזנו בנך מצדקה? nicha lach d'miznu bnach mitzedaka?
Do you want your kids to have to be paid from צדקה
tzedaka funds? So he would also shame him, but not to the,
you know, but not in the same type of public shaming. He
tried to make the person feel embarrassed about his own actions. ולא
אמרן אלא דלא אמיד. v'lo amran ela d'lo amid.
Now all of this is that we'll shame a person but we
won't do anything about it is that he does not have- he's
not a person of means. אבל אמיד aval amid if he's a
person of means, כפינן ליה על כרחיה. kafinan lei al korchei.
Then we would force him. Why would we force him? We would
force him not in terms of a legal obligation to feed your
children, but in terms of the fact that we can force you
to give צדקה. tzedaka. And if we can force you to give
צדקה, tzedaka, well, we can force that צדקה tzedaka to be directed
to your kids. Because you know charity starts at home and they
are a primary obligation, right? If kids- which is actually a fascinating
whole question about מעשר כספים. ma'aser ksafim. Can somebody actually use their
מעשר כספים ma'aser ksafim to pay their tuition bills to a ישיבה
Yeshiva school or food? If technically you're not obligated to feed your
kids, then then really technically it's the ציבור's tzibur responsibility in terms
of צדקה. tzedaka. and any money that you're using to pay feed
your kids is technically צדקה Tzedakah money. So those are interesting questions
within מעשר. Maaser. So anyway, here the גמרא Gemara says that if
he does have a person of means, we can force him to
feed his kids through the through the legal obligation of צדקה. Tzedakah.
כי הא דרבא כפייה לרב נתן בר אמי, Ki ha d'Rava kafyei
l'Rav Natan bar Ami, like Rava forced Rav Natan bar Ami, ואפיק
מיניה ארבע מאה זוזי לצדקה. v'afik minei arba mea zuzei l'tzedakah. Now
this is not a מעשר, Maaser,
this is not a question about feeding the kids, this is just
demonstrating that you can force a person to give their צדקה Tzedakah
responsibilities. Now what is a person's צדקה Tzedakah responsibilities? In terms of
your own personal צדקה Tzedakah responsibilities, you really don't have any. מעשר
כספים Maaser Kesafim is a מנהג, Minhag, it's not really, it's not
in the גמרא. Gemara. The actual, there's no real minimum amount I'm
obligated to give צדקה. Tzedakah. If a poor person asks money from
me then I have to give, but just in terms of a
general, so maybe if the kids are asking for food, that creates
the responsibility. But in general there's no there's no quantifiable minimum really
for צדקה. Tzedakah. But what the city would do is, the city
would arrange its own type of צדקה Tzedakah collections. There would be
קופה Kupa and תמחוי Tamchui and other types of גביית צדקה Gviyat
Tzedakah where they would define what the responsibilities, I mean in a
way it's almost like a sort of tax for social services if
you want to see it that way, you know, but they would
sort of define based on people's, you know, wealth, how much they
had to contribute. So that's what we're talking about. So here you
see and that they were actually empowered to force people to actually
contribute. Yeah, ארבע מאה זוזי arba mea zuzei is probably an exaggeration.
Anyway, so once you see that we have this mechanism of forcing
people to give their צדקה Tzedakah allocation, we could use that for
somebody who has the means to force him to feed his kids.
Okay, so that's the end of that תקנת אושא Takanat Usha that
even though the משנה Mishna says there's no obligation, there was a
תקנת אושא, Takanat Usha, but in the end of the day for
some reason we didn't, it wasn't really adopted and in the end
we are left with public shaming and using these these other types
of indirect means. Let me just point out one quick thing in
תוספות. Tosafos.
Yes, so תוספות Tosafos has a question, famous תוספות, Tosafos, אכפייה רבא,
Achfyei Rava, if you look at תוספות Tosafos he says: ואם תאמר
היכי כפייה משום צדקה והכתיב מתן שכרה בצדה דכתיב למען יברכך או
בגלל דבר זה יברכך השם אלוקיך. V'im tomar heichi kafyei mishum tzedakah
v'haktiv matan sechara b'tzida d'chtiv lemaan yevarechecha o b'glal davar zeh yevarechecha
Hashem Elokecha. So it says that you'll be blessed if you give
צדקה, Tzedakah, ואמרינן בפרק כל הבשר כל מצות עשה שמתן שכרן בצדה
אין בית דין של מטה מוזהרין עליה, v'amrinan b'perek Kol HaBasar kol
mitzvat aseh shematan secharan b'tzida ein beit din shel mata muzharin aleha,
that בית דין Beit Din can force people to fulfill מצות עשה,
Mitzvot Aseh, but like this גמרא Gemara is about forcing a person
to put on טלית Tallit and תפילין, Tefillin, to sit in a
סוכה, Sukkah, but not a מצות עשה Mitzvat Aseh that the תורה
Torah tells you what the reward will be. So therefore how could
you force a person to give צדקה? Tzedakah? So תוספות Tosafos says:
ויש לומר דאכפייה בדברים. V'yesh lomar d'achfyei bidvarim. So it doesn't literally
mean you use physical force, it means you, you know, you persuaded
the person with words, which then gets us pretty much back to
where we started because that's what we were doing anyway with the
guy who wasn't feeding his kids is that we were shaming them
and using our words.
ויש אומרים אי נמי קצבו ביניהם בני העיר, V'yesh omrim ee nami
kitzvu beineihem bnei ha'ir, this is what I was saying, the people
of the city stipulated: לתת כך וכך לכל חודש, latet kach v'kach
l'chol chodesh, to give a certain amount each month. הלכך אכפייה דאמרינן
בפרק קמא דבבא בתרא רשאין בני העיר להסיע על קיצותן, Hilkach achfyei
d'amrinan b'perek kama d'Bava Batra resha'in bnei ha'ir l'hasia al kitzotan, ועוד
דבצדקה איכא תרתי לאוי, v'od d'bitzedakah ika tartei lavei, etc. So תוספות
Tosafos says that maybe here we're not just talking about your biblical
obligation of צדקה Tzedakah which as I said doesn't really have a
minimum anyway, so how much could you force a guy to give?
But maybe we're talking about the obligation that was imposed within the
city for people to contribute and that the people are empowered to
actually use force to have people abide by their sort of city
ordinances and their sort of self-governing type of obligation. And that's important
obviously because it translates into the Middle Ages where the where the
Jewish communities were figuring out the whole mechanisms of self-governance and enforcing,
you know, rules within the community that the community itself had made.
And תוספות Tosafos understands that that's what was going on here. But
the bottom line is is that at most what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is the obligation to feed one's kids, it's either a
תקנה Takana which it doesn't seem like we ruled like in the
end adopted, or a general מצוה Mitzvah of צדקה Tzedakah and then
it raises the question of how do you get somebody to to
do it if he's not doing it. Yes, Charlie? If רמב"ם Rambam
also פסק Paskened for צדקה, Tzedakah, if you don't give the right
amount of צדקה Tzedakah you get lashes. There you go, yes. Is
there a conceptual link between מצוה Mitzvah שכרן בצדה secharan b'tzida and
not and not imposing force because there's a theological motivation built in?
Seems to be, yeah. There's already a kind of positive כפייה kefiya
so to speak.
Yeah, and that God is making it clear that God is going
to take care of it, I guess. But what about מעשר עני
Maaser Ani which is a specific amount of צדקה? Tzedakah? Yeah, but
not with money, not with that was with we're dealing with agriculture.
Okay, back to the גמרא. Gemara. So that was one תקנת אושא
Takanat Usha which tried to restore some balance to the משנה's Mishna
idea that there's no legal obligation, but the גמרא Gemara again concludes
that we don't really adopt that תקנה. Takana. But again as we'll
see later, there is a legal obligation for very small children. So
now the גמרא Gemara moves on to other תקנת אושא Takanat Usha
and this is going to be with the rest of the דף
Daf for today. So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says
like this. אמר רבי אילא אמר ריש לקיש באושא התקינו הכותב כל
נכסיו לבניו. Amar Rabbi Ila amar Reish Lakish b'Usha hitkinu hakotev kol
nechasav l'vanav.
If somebody writes over all of his property to his son while
he's alive.
And why exactly he's doing this? Not clear. Maybe it's a type
of a tax dodge, maybe he's doing it just because he wants
to give it all to his son. הוא ואשתו ניזונין מהם. hu
ve-ishto nizonin mei-hem. He specifically, or his son? No, specifically, could be
all sons, or whatever, doesn't matter. Fine. Anyway, he and his wife
can continue to be supported off of that property. His wife has
rights of מזונות, mezonot, right, as we've learned, her כתובה ketubah rights.
The father doesn't really have any rights. It's his property, he signed
it all over. But nevertheless, somehow they've established, maybe because there's an
assumption that this is what the, you know, what maybe the person's
intent would have been anyway, but certainly it was necessary at some
societal level that the husband and wife can continue to be supported
off of that estate in terms of food and so on. So
מתקיף לה רבי זירא, Matkif lah Rabbi Zeira, Rabbi Zeira challenges. ואיתימא
רב שמואל בר נחמני, ve-itayma Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani, גדולים מזו אמרו,
gedolim mizo amru, they said even a bigger חידוש. chiddush. What was
it? What did they say? We'll explain this in a minute. אלמנתו
ניזונת מנכסיו. almanato nizonet mi-nechasav.
So if they said that his widow can be fed off of
his property, הוא ואשתו מיבעיא, hu ve-ishto mibaya, it goes without saying
he and his wife. What does that mean? דשלח רבין באגרתיה, dishlach
Ravin be-igrateih, that Ravin sent us a letter from ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. מי שמת והניח אלמנה ובת. mi she-meis ve-hiniach almana u-vas.
A person who dies and left behind a widow and a daughter.
Now remember, the widow and the daughter are both entitled to be
supported. Right, the widow because of, you know, the כתובה ketubah obligations,
not only gives her a lump sum payment but allows her to
continue to be supported off of the estate until she takes out
her lump sum payment. And the daughter because of, as we mentioned
before, the daughter's supported by the estate after the person dies until
she gets married. So מי שמת והניח אלמנה ובת. mi she-meis ve-hiniach
almana u-vas. אלמנתו ניזונת מנכסיו. almanato nizonet mi-nechasav. So the אלמנה almana
gets supported off of his property. ניסת הבת. nisais ha-bas. Now let's
say the daughter gets married. And when the daughter gets married, she
takes with her the property. And now the property is with her
and her new husband, and the husband has basically like a rights
over that property. Nevertheless, אלמנתו ניזונת מנכסיו. almanato nizonet mi-nechasav. The widow
continues to be supported off of that property. We're talking like real
estate that even that the daughter took with her after she got
married. That the son-in-law's controlling. That the son-in-law is controlling. מתה הבת,
meisah ha-bas, so
and the daughter dies. אמר רבי יהודה בן אחותו של רבי יוסי
בר חנינא, amar Rabbi Yehuda ben achoso shel Rabbi Yossi bar Chanina,
עלי היה מעשה, alai hayah ma'aseh, that this case happened with me.
ואלמנתו ניזונת מנכסיו, ve-almanato nizonet mi-nechasav, that even though the daughter dies
and now the husband inherits that property, the אלמנה almana continues to
be supported off of that property. So the גמרא Gemara says, so
look, if in a case here where after he's died the property
and it transfers hands to the daughter and from the daughter to
the husband and all of that, the אלמנה almana continues to be
supported off of that property and we don't say, now the question
here all has to do with the issue of שעבודים shibudim and
I'm not going to get into the technical aspects of it, but
if she has a lien on the estate and how much does
that lien continue when it transfers hands and so on. But if
we're going to say that that's true in this case by the
אלמנה almana and the daughter after he's died, how much more so,
says the גמרא, Gemara, when it hasn't really transferred hands? He's just
given it to his son. So meaning there's a question about, clearly
the lien that the rights that they have, you know, would be,
it might be something that if I sell it to another person
and the person spends money and it goes out of my control,
that I might therefore say, well maybe the lien that the wife
has or the daughter has or whatever is limited in those cases
to continue to take that property and to pay off that ongoing
debt. Because part of the challenge here, you know, is like well
why not? Aren't all debts have liens on the property and aren't
they all also supposed to be collected when the property changes hands?
Yes. But this lien is different because this is a lien of
מזונות, mezonot, which is not a fixed amount. Okay, it's an ongoing
regular obligation, not a fixed amount, and the general assumption is that
that would be or the general approach is that that's unfair to
say that if I go ahead and I purchase property from you,
somebody else with not a fixed debt, with an ongoing debt, can
come and constantly be taking that property away from me because of
an ongoing debt that they have to be fed for who knows?
The daughter at least is limited until she becomes a בוגרת. bogeret.
The wife could live for another forty years and she keeps on
having that ongoing debt. So normally the lien does not survive when
it switches hands in the case of feeding the daughter and the
wife. However, if it stays within the estate, like the sons inherit,
then obviously that's when the lien is meant to be exacted. So
here the גמרא Gemara says, if we would say in this case
that they can go ahead and be continued to be fed even
after, not if you sell the property, but the property goes through
the daughter and from the daughter to the husband and the daughter
dies and it really is in a third hand, or not through
a sale, but it's in a third party's hands, you can continue
to be fed. How much more so if you give over your
property to your child, to your son, is it really fundamentally still
within your estate and therefore you should continue to be able to
be fed. Now one חידוש chiddush is also that it's one thing
to say the wife is fed, she has a תנאי כתובה. tenai
ketubah. It's another thing to say that the father is fed, that
the husband is fed. Why is he? He doesn't have any right
to continue to be fed by his estate if he's giving it
away. So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. All right,
let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer. So that's the question. If
it goes to through the daughter to the son-in-law and the widow
can still be fed, how much more so in this case? So
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says: so that's true by the daughter,
by the widow, הוא ואשתו מבעיא hu v'ishto mibaya certainly if you
just gave it to your sons, you and your wife, so even
the man and the wife should be continued to be supported. So
the גמרא Gemara says no. מהו דתימא התם הוא דליכא דטרח, mahu
d'teima hasam hu d'leika detarach,
no, there it's different. The guy is dead. The man is dead,
so we're going to give rights to the widow because again, the
assumption is the widow doesn't have an ability, a reasonable ability to
earn money for herself in the larger society. So there even though
it switched hands and it's in the son-in-law's hands right now, we're
going to continue to allow the widow to be fed. אבל הכא
נטרח לדידיה ולדידה, aval hacha nitrach l'didei u'l'dida,
but here the guy is still alive. He just gave away his
property. So נעבעך, nebach, he doesn't have any money, go out and
get a job! Go out and support yourself and your wife. קא
משמע לן kamashmalan that even though he's still alive, when he gives
it, he writes it all over to his kids, he's still entitled
to continue to be supported through that estate. Sort of like the
King Lear, right? He gives away everything and then they're not taking
care of him, okay? So here it is. So if he gives
away everything, they still have to take care of you. Okay. So
a little dramatic.
The King Lear comparison? Yes. Okay. תא שמע, ta shma, okay fine.
So the גמרא Gemara says: איבעיא להו הלכתא כוותיה דאושא או לא
הלכתא כוותיה דאושא, ibayu lhu hilchasa k'vassa d'Usha o lo hilchasa k'vassa
d'Usha, same type of a question, again fascinating, do we rule like
this תקנת אושא Takanas Usha or not? תא שמע
דרבי חנינא ורבי
יוחנן הוו קיימי, ta shma d'Rabbi Chanina v'Rabbi Yochanan havu kaymi, Rabbi
Yochanan and Rabbi Chanina were standing around. אתא ההוא גברא גחין ונשקיה
לרבי יוחנן אכרעיה, asa hahu gavra gachin v'nashkei l'Rabbi Yochanan akara'ei, bowed
down and kissed Rabbi Yochanan on his legs, on his feet. אמר
ליה רבי חנינא מאי
האי, Amar lei Rabbi Chanina mai hai, so Rabbi Chanina said to
Rabbi Yehonasan: what's going on here? Why is this גברא gavra so,
you know, grateful to you? אמר ליה מאי האי אמר ליה כתיב
נכסיו לבניו הוא, Amar lei mai hai amar lei kosav nechasav l'vanav
hu, he was a guy, he had written over all of his
property to his kids, ועשיתינהו לזוני v'asitinu l'zanei and I forced the
kids to support him. אי אמרת בשלמא לאו דינא, i amras bishlama
lav dina,
if you say granted we don't rule that way, there's not legally
obligated, משום הכי עשיתינהו, mishum hachi asitinu,
that's why you had to force the kids. Okay, and that's why
as רש״י Rashi says he was so grateful. אלא אי אמרת דינא,
ella i amras dina,
but if you say that it's the law, עשיתינהו בעי, asitinu bei,
so of course you have to force
them or one of two ways of reading. Either why do you
have to force them through extra-legal means, just have them obligated to
pay? Or the other way of reading it is, of course you
had to force them because they were legally obligated, so why was
he so grateful? But either way what it boils down to is
the fact that he was so grateful shows that it wasn't a
strict legal obligation. So again quite fascinating, you have these two תקנות
אושא Takanos Usha which the גמרא Gemara says we still deal with
in more ways of persuasion or social pressure, but we don't actually
rule like them even though they're there, even though it seems like
they're pretty necessary. So I can't really understand why we wouldn't, why
since the facts are reflecting the idea that they're necessary, legally speaking
you would think that the סנהדרין Sanhedrin makes a תקנה takanah you
have to keep by it, why the, why it developed that it
was assumed that they didn't really adopt the תקנת אושא, Takanas Usha,
I don't know. Now we get to the third תקנת אושא, Takanas
Usha, perhaps the most famous one. אמר רבי אילעא, Amar Rabbi Il'a,
באושא התקינו המבזבז אל יבזבז יותר מחומש. b'Usha hatkinu hamvazbez al yevazbez
yoser michomesh.
Somebody that,
yeah not word of waste, that like I don't know, that is
profligate with his money, that scatters his money, basically gives away all
of his money to צדקה, tzedakah, he can't give away more than
twenty percent.
Now by the way what's important in the in the historical context
is that there were definitely like some of the stories in the
Christian gospels is about people giving away all of their money and
and making themselves impoverished and order and therefore following, you know, in
order to be a follower of Jesus. You know, the Rabbis were
very much against that. They said it's not helpful to not only
is it not helpful to society and yourself, it's not helpful to
the poor. If you're a person that's wealthy and able to make
a lot of money, keep on making a lot of money and
just give, you know, give regularly to the poor. Don't go ahead
and impoverish yourself. And that's what the גמרא Gemara says here.
תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, המבזבז אל יבזבז
יותר מחומש שמא יצטרך לבריות, hamvazbez al yevazbez yoser michomesh shema yitzarech
labriyos,
maybe you will yourself become poor. Even more than twenty percent. Doesn't
even say don't give away a hundred percent. Don't even give away
more than twenty percent. You know, maybe you'll fall on hard times
and then you'll need other people's support and you're in a very
nice situation right now that you're self-sufficient
and better to, you know, don't kill the goose that gives the
golden eggs. You're self-sufficient and continue to be productive and continue to
give a reasonable amount each year to צדקה. tzedakah. That's stable social...
right exactly. ומעשה באחד שביקש לבזבז יותר מחומש, u'maaseh b'echad shebikeish levazbez
yoser michomesh, there was a story about somebody who wanted to give
away more than twenty percent, ולא הניח לו חבירו v'lo hiniach lo
chaveiro and his friend did not allow him. ומנו הוא וזה רבי
ישבב, u'manu hu v'ze Rabbi Yeshevav, and who was it? This is
רבי ישבב. Rabbi Yeshevav. ואמרי ליה רבי ישבב v'amri lei Rabbi Yeshevav
or some say רבי ישבב Rabbi Yeshevav who's the one who wanted
to give away ולא הניח לו חבירו ומנו רבי עקיבא, v'lo hiniach
lo chaveiro manu Rabbi Akiva, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva didn't allow
him. Okay. אמר רב נחמן ואיתימא רב אחא בר יעקב, Amar Rav
Nachman v'isayma Rav Acha bar Yaakov, מאי קרא, mai kra, where's the
verse that you see this? וכל אשר תתן לי, v'chol asher titten
li, everything you give me. עשר אעשרנו לך. aseir a'asrenu lach. I'll
give two, so it's reading it, I'll give two מעשרס. maisers.
I'll give twenty percent. Okay, twenty percent, not more than twenty percent.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says הא לא דמי איסורא בתרא לאיסורא
קמא. Ha lo dami isura basra l'isura kama. Wait a minute.
The second tenth is not the same as the first tenth. Right?
If you have a hundred and you give away ten percent, then
you're left with ninety. You give away ten percent of what's left,
that's nine. Right? Ten percent of ninety is nine. So it's nineteen
percent, it's not twenty percent. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב
אשי Amar Rav Ashi אעשרנו לך a'asrenu lach בתרא כקמא. basra k'kama.
No, עשר אעשרנו. aseir a'asrenu.
The אעשרנו asrenu means going back to the original amount. The second
מעשר ma'aser will be like the first מעשר ma'aser on the original
amount, so the total will be twenty percent. Okay. Now let's read
one more thing and then I'll go back and say something about
this. אמר רב שימי בר אשי בשמועות הללו מסתמטות והולכות. Amar Rav
Shimi bar Ashi b'shmuos hallalu mismat'os v'holchos.
These שמועות shmuos are, now מסתמטות והולכות mismat'os v'holchos sounds like it's
some type of a statement about like they get weaker, less powerful,
but all he really means is that the chain of tradition, if
you looked at the three תקנות אושא, takanos Usha, each chain is
shorter than the previous chain. The first chain
was what was it? It was, yeah, אמר רבי אילעא אמר ריש
לקיש משום רבי יהודה בר חנינא. Amar Rabbi Ilai Amar Reish Lakish
mishum Rabbi Yehuda bar Chanina. So
it was רבי אילעא, Rabbi Ilai, ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, רבי יהודה
בר
חנינא. Rabbi Yehuda bar Chanina. This next stage of tradition was אמר
ריש לקיש משום רבי יהודה בר חנינא. Amar Reish Lakish mishum Rabbi
Yehuda bar Chanina.
The third statement of אושא Usha was just אמר רבי יהודה בר
חנינא. Amar Rabbi Yehuda bar Chanina. So it's all the same stage.
I'm sorry, did I do it the wrong way? No, it was
אמר רבי אילעא אמר ריש לקיש Amar Rabbi Ilai Amar Reish Lakish
and the third stage was just אמר רבי אילעא. Amar Rabbi Ilai.
Okay, so it was normally was like A B C אושא, Usha,
and then it was just A B אושא, Usha, and then it
was just A אושא. Usha. So you get only like the last
person in the chain. Now the funny thing is, of course, as
I've said before, I don't understand, to get all the way to
רבי אילעא, Rabbi Ilai, it had to pass down those generations. So
what difference does it make if you're quoting prior generations or you're
not? So the answer is what those chains of traditions mean when
they are quoting mean who is the first one not just to
have taught this to his students and passed it down, but who
is the first one to have effectively published it? Like, you know,
publicly sort of
said whether it's a מימרא, memra, whether it's a historical statement of
תקנת אושא takanas Usha and so on. So if it's אמר amar
just, it's אמר רבי אילעא Amar Rabbi Ilai means until רבי אילעא
Rabbi Ilai nobody has heard of this. Now רבי אילעא Rabbi Ilai
is saying that he got it through his רביים rebeim and so
on, presumably you needed that chain of tradition for it to get
down from תקנת אושא, takanas Usha, but it hadn't been stated until
רבי אילעא. Rabbi Ilai. So what we're saying is that these three
תקנות, takanos, each one only surfaced at a later stage. The interesting
irony is, is that while the גמרא's Gemara clear we don't פסקן
pasken the first two תקנות, takanos, this idea of צדקה tzedaka we
do פסקן, pasken, that you're not supposed to, I don't know, that
you're not supposed to give more than the twenty percent. So that's
one thing. Let's just by the way the גמרא Gemara has a
little סימנך, simancha, the גמרא Gemara says like this: וסימנך v'simancha to
help to remember the order which one has the longer chain of
tradition, קטנים כתבו בזבזו. ktanim kisfu bizbezu. The children wrote down and
squandered. So what does that mean? The first one was about your
obligation to feed your minor children. The second one was about writing
all of your property, כתב, koseiv, writing all your property to your
kids, and the third one was about squandering your money to צדקה.
tzedaka.
Fine. Now, right, קטנים ktanim is the longest one. Oh, it's interesting,
okay. Anyway, so now I want to do other things about this
צדקה tzedaka thing. Number one is, or three other things. Number one
is תוספות. Tosfos. First of all, the idea of twenty percent as
the גמרא Gemara indicates עשר אעשרנו, aseir a'asrenu, pretty much parallels the
normal amount that people would have to give when they were a
world of תרומות ומעשרות, trumas u'maisros, right? They'd have to give תרומה,
truma, and then מעשר, ma'aser, and then מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, and
even though the גמרא Gemara points out that's more like nineteen percent,
but plus תרומה truma maybe it's nineteen and a half percent, then
you add the other things that you would give, ביכורים bikkurim and
the מתנות matanos of the בהמות, beheimos, and even that orva, well
מתנות matanos of the בהמות beheimos aren't a good comparison because they're
not from the same source of income. Anyway, it's pretty close to
what you would normally give. So on the one hand while it
sounds like oh you want to be very prolific, we'll let you
give twice as much as the standard, in the time that you're
giving you know from your grain it's exactly what the standard is
although it's true that there it doesn't always go to the עניים,
ani'im, like a lot of it goes to the כהנים kohanim and
the לויים levi'im and so on, but it goes towards religious purposes
so it's out of your pocket, true. So that's number one. Number
two is תוספות Tosfos has, so then the question becomes twenty percent
of what? So take a look at תוספות, Tosfos, תוספות Tosfos says
אל יבזבז יותר מחומש, al yevazbez yoser m'chomesh,
תוספות Tosfos says a very important question: מפרש בירושלמי שפעם ראשונה יכול
לבזבז חומש חומש ומכאן ואילך בכל שנה ושנה יתן חומש מהרווח. m'faresh
bi'yerushalmi she-pa'am rishona yachol l'vazbez chomesh chomesh, u'mikan va'eilech b'chol shana v'shana
yitein chomesh me'harevach.
So the first twenty percent is twenty percent of your principal, then
it is a big חידוש chiddush because normally when you give מעשר
ma'aser you're giving מעשר ma'aser off of your income. Here it's talking
about you actually want to give away your principal, you want to
give away your collected assets. So but then the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says
don't go ahead and give twenty percent each year of your assets
because then pretty soon even though it would not be five years
because it's like whatever it is, you know, 20% of what's left,
but pretty soon you'll be left with very very little. So there's
a question about the total assets as opposed to your income. And
the final question that gets raised is what's the story nowadays when
we're dealing with like the mega-rich? You know, Bill Gates came and
wanted to give a donation to your שול shul and he wanted
to give 40% of his total assets. Would you say oh no,
I'm sorry, we only allow 20%? Right, if somebody has billions of
dollars, does it have the same rule? But maybe it does. Maybe
if those billions of dollars are working in the economy and helping
to generate more and more income, then maybe it should be just
as much that, yeah, don't give so much away at one time.
Wait a minute, yeah.
Which generation was Rabbi Elai? I don't know. He's after ריש לקיש.
Resh Lakish. Yeah, obviously, I'm thinking how much later because the final
one he's citing what happened at אושא, Usha, which was a minute
ago. Even ריש לקיש Resh Lakish in אושא Usha talking about hundreds
of years or whatever. Yeah, no, but then sort of what Bloomberg
did, since he was so good at making money, he was like
saying like I'm not going to give it all like, you know,
20 years ago, I could be making so much more and give
so much more later. Right, right. A better comparison was Michael Bloomberg
because he actually is Jewish.
All right, moving on. So good. All right, and so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבי יצחק. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak.
So that's three תקנות takkanos with אושא. Usha. Now we get to
another one.
אמר רבי יצחק באושא התקינו שיהא אדם מתגלגל עם בנו עד שתים
עשרה שנה. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak be-Usha hitkinu she-adam mitgalgel im beno ad
shem-esrei shana. Now we get back to obligations to the kids, but
this is not the feeding obligation, but it's the Torah obligation. And
it's also a little bit, as we'll see, a little bit not
just about rights, but about restrictions as well. Or not just about
obligations, but about rights and restrictions. So in אושא Usha they established
that a person should roll along with his son, meaning in terms
of trying to educate him in Torah till he's 12 years old.
מכאן ואילך, Mikan ve-eilakh, meaning and sort of as רש"י Rashi says,
you know, be more of a nurturing, supportive type of an educator.
If already at 12 he's not putting his mind to his studies
and he's not succeeding, יורד לו לחייו. yorde lo le-hayyav. Then you
go into his very livelihood, or what does it mean livelihood? Into
his life. You're more invasive. So רש"י Rashi says what does invasive
mean? רש"י Rashi says it either means that you use physical force,
you slap him or worse, you know, you beat him. Exactly, or
you hold back his food. That'll get him to study better. No
food until you study better. Right. The beatings will continue until the
morale improves. So anyway,
so רש"י Rashi says יורד לו לחייו בדוחקא ברצועה yorde lo le-hayyav
be-doto be-ratzu'a to beat him with a strap, או בחוסך לחם o
be-hosekh lechem and hold back the food. All right, so that's pretty...
I understand, I understand. Makes you realize a very different type of
an educational system or parenting also that was done at those times.
Okay. איני, Eini, is this really true? ואמר ליה רב לרב שמואל
בר שילת, Ve-amar lei Rav le-Rav Shmuel bar Shilat, רב Rav said
to רב שמואל בר שילת, Rav Shmuel bar Shilat, בציר מבר שש
לא תקבל, batzir mi-bar sheish lo takbil, בר שש קבל. Bar sheish
kabil. So רב שמואל בר שילת Rav Shmuel bar Shilat was a
teacher, was a חדר cheder teacher, and he says don't accept kids
into the חדר cheder under six years old. Don't accept them into
the school, right. So the same way now, first grade starts at
the age of six, right, no kindergarten. Don't accept them under the
age of six. Starting at six years old קבל, kabil, accept them
into the school, וספי ליה כתורא, ve-safi lei ke-tora, and stuff it
down their throats like an ox, right, you know you would force-feed
oxen, you would like really, like, you know, you put the food
ממש mamash like into the throat itself so the ox could do
nothing but swallow it. So stuff it down their throats. One minute.
So
you see that you force-feed them, presumably it means that you use
some real force in order to do it. And you're saying that
you don't use force till 12 years old. So the גמרא Gemara
says: אין וספי ליה כתורא. In safi lei ke-tora. Yes, you stuff
it down their throats. מיהו אינו יורד לו לחייו עד לאחר שתים
עשרה שנה. Mihu eino yorde lo le-hayyav ad le-achar sheim-esrei shana. But
you don't actually, you know, get down, you're not invasive into their
lives by again beating them or punishing them or whatever until 12
years. So it's one thing to have a very demanding school and
a demanding curriculum. It's another thing to be, you know, to actually
be invasive physically and otherwise in order to make sure that they
get it. Yes, Charlie, you want to ask a question? The משנה
Mishnah in אבות Avos says age five. Right, so the תוספות Tosafos
tries to reconcile this with the משנה Mishnah in אבות. Avos. Take
a look at תוספות. Tosafos. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. ואיבעית אימא, Ve-iba'it eima, if you want, לא קשיא. lo kashya.
It's not... whether it's six or 12. הא למקרא הא למשנה. Ha
le-mikra ha le-mishna. At six, then you actually can, you know, you
can be, you can use force to get them to learn Torah,
but in terms of when it comes to משנה, Mishnah, there until
they're 12, you give them until 12 to be more nurturing and
only at 12 on do you start using some force. Whatever. דאמר
אביי, De-amar Abbaye, right, so it's not... it doesn't all reconcile. אמרה
לי אם, Amerah lei eim, my mother, which wasn't his mother, his
nursemaid said to him: בר שש למקרא, Bar sheish le-mikra, at the
age of six you start learning Torah. Again, doesn't fit with פרקי
אבות Pirkei Avos which says
five. בר עשר למשנה, Bar esser le-mishna, ten you start learning משנה.
Mishnah. בר תלסר לתעניתא, Bar telasar le-tanisa, when you're 13, מעת לעת,
me-eis le-eis, when you're 13 you have to fast for a full...
full day. And by—and by girls at twelve they have to start
fasting for a full day. Under that obviously then they're בר בת
מצוה. Bar Bas Mitzvah. רש"י תוספות Rashi Tosfos say it means a
year before בר מצוה. Bar Mitzvah. תוספות Tosfos disagrees. Anyway, before that
you start partial fasts, but the full fast is only at בר
בת מצוה. Bar Bas Mitzvah. Again, the problem here is that it
says ten for משנה, Mishna, we're saying twelve, so whatever, from ten
to twelve you do it in a more nurturing way, but at
twelve you start using some real force. Okay, אמר אביי. Amar Abaye.
Now that we're talking about young kids and אביי's Abaye nursemaids and
her wisdom, we're going to go on with it. אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, אמרה לי אם, Amra li em, my nursemaid said to me,
האי בר שית דטרקא ליה עקרבא, Hai bar shis detarkala akrava, if
a six-year-old kid, a scorpion bites him, ביומא דמשלם שית, Beyoma demishlem
shis, on the day that he—on his birthday, the day he became
six, לא חיי, lo chaye, he won't live. מאי אסותיה? Mai asusei?
Now, what—how do you cure him? So it's funny, he won't live,
you won't cure him. So רש"י Rashi says he won't live unless
you do the following cure. Okay, תוספות Tosfos says he won't live,
here's what you have to do to prevent him as a preventative
measure, so that if it happens he won't die. But רש"י Rashi
is probably a little more פשט. pshat. Okay, he won't live unless
you do the following thing. מאי אסותיה, Mai asusei, what's the cure?
מררתא דדייא, Mrarta dedaya, you take the bitterness—or it might mean the
gallbladder—how does it translate מררתא? mrarta? Is it the—is it the poison
or the gallbladder? The bile, the bile. Okay, the bile of a
דייא, daya, which is a particular bird in the תורה, Torah, חיורתא,
chivarta, a white one, white vulture. Thank you. The bile of a
white vulture. בשיכרא, Beshichra, you somehow boil it with mead. נשפיה Nishpaya
and you rub it on the—all either all over the child or
at the place of the wound. ונשקיה Venashkeya and have him drink
it. האי בר שית דטרקא ליה זיבורא, Hai bar shis detarkala zibura,
now if a hornet stings a six-year-old, ביומא דמשלם שית, Beyoma demishlem
shis, on the day he becomes six, לא חיי, lo chaye, he
won't live. מאי אסותיה, Mai asusei, what's the cure? אצפתא דדיקלא, Atzpasa
dedikla, you take some type of a—of a—of a vine that grows
around the palm tree, במיא, bemaya, and you boil it in water.
ונשפיה ונשקיה, Venishpaya venashkeya, you rub it on him and you have
him drink it. אמר רב קטינא, Amar Rav Katina, כל המכניס את
בנו פחות מבן שית. Kol hamachnis es bno pachos miben shesh. Now
again we're dealing with educating your kids at a young age. Okay,
anybody who puts, brings his kid into the חדר cheder under six
years old, רץ אחריו ואינו מגיעו. ratz acharav ve'aino magio. So you'll
have to run after him and you won't reach up to him.
Now, what does that mean? It could mean he'll be intellectually advanced,
as the גמרא's Gemara going to say in a minute. But the
גמרא Gemara apparently here, רש"י Rashi says, but it's clear from the
גמרא Gemara later, understands it means you're going to spend all of
your time chasing after him to try to—to try to get him
to be healthy, no, to try to get him to be healthy,
and you won't accomplish it. Because meaning again, he's too delicate at
that age to be put into a full day of חדר, cheder,
especially if they're using the ruler and the strap. And therefore you're
going to be spending all of your time trying to, you know,
he's not ready for it yet, trying to protect him or get
him strength—strong. So the גמרא Gemara says, איכא דאמרי, ika de'amri, some
say, חביריו רצים אחריו ואין מגיעין אותו, chaveirav ratzim acharav ve'ein magiin
oso, that his colleagues, his peers, his classmates, will constantly try to
run after him, and this is talking about intellectual achievement. He'll be
so far ahead of them that everybody will be running to—right, everybody
will be running to keep—to keep up with him. So the גמרא
Gemara says, ואין מגיעין אותו. ve'ein magiin oso. ותרוייהו איתנהו, Uservaihu isnahu,
and they're both true. חליש, Chalish, he'll be weak because he was
a little bit too young to start school. וגמיר, Vegamir, but he'll
be very intellectually accomplished. Okay, it's like, you know, the stories about
the parents that try—like trained their kid from the age he was
an infant to be a chess champion. Have you heard about these
stories? Anyway, they—actually you're able to do those types of things, but
at a very high cost. Okay, so fine, he'll be—the kid will
be very accomplished, but he's going to be very sickly and weak.
All right. איבעית אימא, Iba'is eima, הא דכחיש הא דבריא. ha dechachish
ha debaria. It depends. If he's weak, then you don't start him
under six. If he's strong, you start him under six. All right.
Anyway, that is the end about that discussion about, what do you
call it, educating the kids at a young age. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Yeah. So about getting back to this
חומש Chumash thing, is that same thing applies to like מצוות mitzvos
of, like you know, you don't spend a certain amount, like you
know, of lulav and the esrog, like... Yeah, so there's a question.
By מצוות mitzvos it's another discussion about spending a third, a third
more than the going rate, or whatever. How much is the idea?
Yeah, Michael makes a good point of mentioning that the idea of—I'll
just say one sentence about this, a very important point. That the
idea of not spending more than a fifth for צדקה tzedakah gets
translated, there's two other numbers that are used for מצוות. mitzvos. One
is that idea of how much do you expend for הידור מצוה.
hiddur mitzvah. And some say a fifth, some say a third. But
there the idea is more than the going rate was. Like if
the standard אתרוג esrog is fifty dollars, then don't spend a hundred
dollars for a מהודר אתרוג. mehudur esrog. Spend, you know, thirty percent
more than that, or fifty percent more than that, seventy-five dollars for
a מהודר אתרוג. mehudur esrog. Okay, but then the question is how
do you establish the baseline? More importantly, there's the idea about an
economic threshold for not doing a מצות עשה. mitzvas asei. Whereas this
גמרא Gemara speaks about צדקה, tzedakah, and if you're not giving a
fifth, you're still giving something, you're still giving a dollar, you're not
not doing it. But interestingly, the ראשונים Rishonim and the פוסקים Poskim
wind up using this as a model. for saying that if a
מצות עשה, Mitzvas Asei, not a לא תעשה, Lo Saasei, but if
the lack of performance of an עשה Asei is going to cost
more than twenty percent of your of your—well, the question is, does
it mean your annual income, does it mean your current assets, which
is the תוספות Tosafos raise, but more than twenty percent, then you
don't have to do a מצות עשה. Mitzvas Asei. So let's say,
for example, I have—let's let's let's—yeah, I mean even תרומות, Terumos, but
let's say I've got סוכה, Sukkah, לולב, Lulav, and אתרוג. Esrog. I'm
not sure I have a penny to my name. Do I have
to—and nobody's going to lend me a לולב Lulav and an אתרוג.
Esrog. Do I have to borrow money and go in debt or,
you know, spend my last dollar that I would have used to
put food on my table to buy a לולב Lulav and an
אתרוג? Esrog? And the answer is no, and they wind up using
this גמרא Gemara about the fifth and the twenty percent as a
model for that, although again, it's a questionable model, but that becomes
a very important principle in הלכה, Halacha, which is that the lack
of performance of עשה, Asei, there are thresholds for it. And there
are monetary thresholds and there are also other types of thresholds, you
know, and things that would be so like, you know, completely like,
you know, as like, whatever, פוסקים Poskim discuss situations which would be
comparable to or more, you know, not just imposing, but whatever, are
more onerous than just twenty percent of your money, also serves as
a threshold for when do you have to do a מצות עשה.
Mitzvas Asei. Yes, כיבוד אב ואם Kibbud Av Va'eim has a threshold
as well. Well, yeah, okay, yes, but that's internal within כיבוד אב
ואם. Kibbud Av Va'eim. Okay, as for the נודע ביהודה's Noda B'Yehudah
exceptions like ארבע כוסות, Arba Kosos, right, if I remember correctly, yeah,
right, so does that like supersede the limit? Yeah, so that's a
good point, right, אפילו—so, Afilu so the idea that there are a
few cases where you're supposed to borrow money. I mean, the case
of the ארבע כוסות, Arba Kosos, since we're coming up for פסח,
Pesach, אפילו עני המתפרנס מן הצדקה אל יפחתו לו, Afilu Oni Ha'misparnes
Min Ha'tzedaka Al Yifchesu Lo, the רשב"ם Rashbam and רש"י Rashi already
point out יפחתו לו Yifchesu Lo is others should not be פוחת
Pocheis from him, it's our communal obligation to make sure he has
ארבע כוסות, Arba Kosos, but you are correct that there are some
places where we say that you are supposed to borrow money in
order to do it, but those are the exceptions. Yeah, I mean,
you know, there's other cases also like, you know, the מנחת חינוך
Minchas Chinuch says like how could there be a מצווה Mitzvah to
go to war, it's פיקוח נפש, Pikuach Nefesh, you know, and it's
a מצות עשה, Mitzvas Asei, you're not supposed to—it's not one of
the יהרג ואל יעבור, Yehareg V'al Yaavor, it's not one of the
things you're supposed to risk your life, and it's only a מצות
עשה Mitzvas Asei anyway. Okay, or how could I have an obligation
to educate my kids? That's more than a fifth of my income,
you know. So, so there are some מצוות Mitzvos where it's incorporated
into the understanding of that's your obligation, and there's some exceptions, but
this also still does become a general rule. Okay, so that was
another תקנת אושא Takanas Usha about when you start educating your kids
and when you start using, you know, more forceful messages—methods I should
say. Now we get onto another תקנת אושא. Takanas Usha. אמר רב
יוסף בר חנינא באושא התקינו האשה שמכרה בנכסי מלוג בחיי בעלה. Amar
Rav Yosef bar Chanina Be'Usha Tiknu Ha'ishah She'machra Be'nichsei Melog Be'chayei Ba'alah.
This is also one of the more famous תקנות אושא, Takanos Usha,
presumably because we rule like it. If a woman sells—remember what the
נכסי מלוג Nichsei Melog are. They're property that she brings into the
marriage that she has title to, and that the husband gets the
פירות, Peiros, but she retains title to. Liquid assets? No, it doesn't
have to be liquid assets. She owns a farm somewhere. Okay, but
she retains title to, but the husband gets the—the husband gets the
פירות, Peiros, the benefits. And now, so she—she retains title, she's going
to sell it to somebody. So she sells it to somebody else
while her father—while the husband's alive, the husband still gets the פירות,
Peiros, okay, then she die—because he still has the right to the
פירות Peiros of the property. Then she dies. Now that she's dead,
the husband inherits the נכסי מלוג, Nichsei Melog, okay, he inherits his
wife. But this property was already sold. In אושא Usha they said,
no, he can still collect that property even though she sold it,
he is still considered to have enough of a—of not just a
lien and not just a right to the פירות, Peiros, but essentially
be seen as an owner of that property, he will at least,
you know, in—in that the fact that when he—when she dies, he
will actually be able to take title of it. Okay, which is
באושא התקינו, Be'Usha Tiknu, in אושא Usha they established, האשה שמכרה בנכסי
מלוג בחיי בעלה, Ha'ishah She'machra Be'nichsei Melog Be'chayei Ba'alah, the woman sold
these נכסי מלוג Nichsei Melog while her husband was alive, ומתה, U'meisah,
and then she dies, הבעל מוציא מיד הלקוחות, Ha'baal Motzi Mi'yad Ha'lekuchos,
the—the husband can take away from the purchasers. She doesn't own it
so much to prevent the sale from going through, but he owns
it enough to take it. Of course you realize the irony, she
sold it to these people and these—these people that bought it don't
get to eat the פירות Peiros because he still has rights to
the פירות, Peiros, and then to say, okay fine, but when she
dies then they'll—or he gets title—no, but when she dies actually then
they lose it. So what do they get? They got nothing out
of it. Why did they buy? All they got out of it
would be that if he were to die, then they would become
full owners of it. But if she dies first, if he were
to die before her. But if she dies first, then they got
nothing out of it. Now maybe they can go back to the
woman and get their money back, that has to do also with
אחריות Achrayus and so on. Okay, but they treated him not just
as somebody who has rights to the פירות, Peiros, but actually as
an owner. תוספות Tosafos points out that based on the debate of
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ריש לקיש Reish Lakish whether קניין פירות כקניין
הגוף דמי, Kinyan Peiros Ke'kinyan Ha'guf Dami, right, whether owning the פירות
Peiros is like owning the—the property itself, you might not need תקנת
אושא. Takanas Usha. He discusses whether you would or not, but the
point is the husband who has rights to the פירות Peiros is
considered to be an owner and therefore with these consequences that if
she dies first, he will take it away from whoever else is
in possession of it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this... As for רב יצחק בר יוסף Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef ורבי
אבהו, v'Rebi Abahu, רב יצחק בר יוסף Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef and
רבי אבהו Rebi Abahu דהוה קאי באוכלוסא דאושא. d'havei kai b'uchlusa d'Usha.
He was there giving a שיעור shiur amongst the masses in אושא.
Usha. אמר ליה, amar leh, he said, מאן מרה דשמעתא דאושא? man
marei d'shmata d'Usha? Who is like the head of the teachings of
אושא, Usha, you know, the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva here? So אמר
ליה, amar leh, רבי יאשיה בר חנינא. Rebi Yoshi bar Chanina. It’s
רבי יאשיה בר חנינא. Rebi Yoshi bar Chanina. תנא מיניה ארבעין זימנין,
tana minei arbin zimnin, he taught him it forty times I should
say, to remember who was the... it’s like me, I can't remember
anybody's name. So he says he had to learn forty times who
was the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva there in אושא, Usha, ודמי ליה
כמאן דמנח בכיסתיה, v'dami lei k'man d'manach b'chistey, and it was like
he put it in his back pocket. It’s so funny, normally you
say that about like, like you know, complicated הלכה halachic rulings, here
it’s to figure out who the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva was. But
anyway, but that reminds us that if you remember the... the what
do you call it? Right, it was... no, forget it... רבי יהודה
בר חנינא, Rebi Yehudah bar Chanina, maybe done the same... רבי יהושע
בר יאשיה... Rebi Yehoshua bar Yoshi... what?... אמר ליה רבי יהושע בר
יאשיה amar leh Rebi Yehoshua bar Yoshi in terms of the teaching.
Where are you? עמוד א. Amud Alef. Oh yeah, the first one
was באושי התקינו b'Ushi hatkinu משום רבי יהודה בר חנינא mishum Rebi
Yehudah bar Chanina and they say some say רבי יוסי, Rebi Yosi,
right? So that's what I was wondering, right. So here it's רבי
יאשיה בר חנינא, Rebi Yoshi bar Chanina, all the previous teachings of
אושא Usha were in the name of רבי יהודה בר חנינא, Rebi
Yehudah bar Chanina, but some, maybe that's why he had to learn
it forty times to make sure it was the same or different
person. Anyway, right. Okay, anyway, but it could be that all the
traditions of אושא Usha we were telling before was in the name
exactly here of רבי יאשיה בר חנינא. Rebi Yoshi bar Chanina. Okay,
the גמרא Gemara does in a very... "suspect" isn't the right word,
but very particular about who said what. Right. And you often find,
you know, different versions... right... maybe he said this... but you know,
so they say one said this, one said that. But it's very
important to the גמרא Gemara exactly what the chain... Absolutely. But the
idea of forty times to remember a name seems a little funny...
yeah, okay... because it's embarrassing. It gets kind of awkward, you want
to answer him... fine. Now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay. אשרי שומרי
משפט עושה צדקה בכל עת. Ashrei shomrei mishpat oseih tzedakah b'chol eis.
Praises the one who does... who does justice, who does righteousness at
all times. You know, צדקה tzedakah in תנ"ך Tanakh is not צדקה
tzedakah of gift to the poor and charity. It's righteousness, but the
גמרא Gemara reads it as our contemporary meaning of צדקה. tzedakah. וכי
אפשר לעשות צדקה בכל עת? v'chi efshar la'asos tzedakah b'chol eis? Can
somebody constantly be giving צדקה? tzedakah? דרשו רבותינו שביבנה, darshu raboseinu she'b'Yavneh,
on Yavneh they interpreted it, ואמרי לה רבי אליעזר, v'amrei lah Rebi
Eliezer, זה הזן בניו ובנותיו כשהם קטנים. zeh hazan banav u'bnosav k'shehein
ktanim. We come full circle to what we started. Since you're not
legally obligated to feed your kids, if you are providing for your
kids, then you're doing צדקה בכל עת. tzedakah b'chol eis. They're living
in my house rent-free, they're eating from my food without paying for
it. So every single, you know, every single day you're supporting your
kids and you don't legally have to. So there you go, that
is צדקה בכל עת. tzedakah b'chol eis. And that ties back also
to the idea that if a guy isn't doing it, you can
force him to give the צדקה. tzedakah. רבי שמואל בר נחמני Rebi
Shmuel bar Nachmani אמר, amar, זה המגדל יתום ויתומה בתוך ביתו. zeh
hamigadel yasom v'yesomah b'soch beiso. This is somebody who raises an orphan
boy or girl in their house. Because that's maybe... maybe as opposed
to the other thing which might technically be צדקה tzedakah but at
a societal level of course everybody is doing it. So, you know,
it's nothing special about that, even if technically צדקה, tzedakah, but raising
orphans, taking in foster kids or adopting a child, raising an orphan,
right, ומשיאן, u'masian, and then you get them married off so then
they're able to be provided for even after you, right? Because now
they're married and so on, either the boy is now self-sufficient, he's
able to take a wife, or the woman is now being protected
for. So then you've really totally, you've constantly, you've ensured their future
success and you've raised them in a way that's exceptional, that's not
everybody takes care of their own kids. ומשיאן לאחרים. u'masian l'acheirim. I'm
sorry, ומשיאן. u'masian. So that's a very nice interpretation by parallel about
something similar to raising your kids but again in a way that's
not normally done. הון ועושר בביתו וצדקתו עומדת לעד. hon va'osher b'beiso
v'tzidkaso omedes la'ad. A person has wealth in his house and his
righteousness stands for future generations. Again, here reading it as צדקה. tzedakah.
רב הונא ורב חסדא. Rav Huna v'Rav Chisda. חד אמר chad amar
זה הלומד תורה ומלמדה. zeh halomed Torah u'm'lamdah. You learn תורה, Torah,
so you have this wealth, intellectual תורה Torah wealth in your house,
and it's for all generations, for future, because you teach to others
and then those teachings get taught to others and it continues on
forever. חד אמר chad amar זה הכותב תורה נביאים וכתובים ומשאילן לאחרים.
zeh hakosev Torah Nevi'im u'Chsuvim u'mash'ilan l'acheirim. That you write the ספרי
תנ"ך sifrei Tanakh and you lend them, so that's עומדת לעד, omedes
la'ad, it's actually a physical concrete thing that now will continue to
educate other people. וראה בנים לבניך שלום על ישראל. u're'eih vanim l'vanecha
shalom al Yisrael. You'll see children to your children and there'll be
peace in Israel. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, amar Rebi Yehoshua ben
Levi, כיון שבנים לבניך שלום על ישראל. keivan she'banim l'vanecha shalom al
Yisrael. Once your kids have children, then there'll be שלום. shalom. Why?
דלא אתו לידי חליצה ויבום. d'lo asu l'yidei chalitzah v'yibum. It won't
lead to going back to the last מסכת. masechet. Right, if your
children have children, there's not going to be any חליצה chalitzah issues
and presumably, although we didn't really see so much of this, you
know, that leads to contention. Should who's going to do the חליצה,
chalitzah, who's going to do the יבום, yibum, the whole act of
חליצה chalitzah is degrading. Recently a whole report in the... in the
press there from Israel, I don't know if you've read about, there
was a public חליצה chalitzah ceremony and people were... were like so
deeply offended, etc. Anyway, so this will avoid all those issues. רבי
שמואל בר נחמני Rebi Shmuel bar Nachmani אמר amar כיון שבנים לבניך
שלום על דייני ישראל. keivan she'banim l'vanecha shalom al dayanai Yisrael. ישראל.
Yisrael. No, the judges, if you have all these children, the judges
will have it easier. Why? דלא אתו לאינצויי, de-lo asi l'insuei, they
won't be fighting. Why won't they be fighting? They won't be fighting
over the ירושה. yerusha. So I don't know what בן עזאי Ben
Azzai whether he means they won't be fighting over the ירושה, yerusha,
they the biggest fights over the ירושה yerusha is you've got a
big family and everybody is arguing in the court. So רש"י Rashi
says the fights are normally talking about the fights is that if
there is no direct descendants, then there's a whole big question about
who is the closest relative. Whereas this way, you know, then the
fights of ירושה yerusha tend to be when there's when there's like
contested wills or whatever. If nobody's writing a will and it's just
simply following the rules of ירושה yerusha and you know who all
the heirs are, but nevertheless, really no fights, like even if you
know who the heirs are, like no, I don't get the house,
you get the house, I get the car, whatever. Anyway, all right,
but that's how we're ending it. Okay. Now, זה מדרש שדרש רבי,
zeh midrash she-darash rabbi, what time is it? We have four minutes,
we'll turn the page. דרש רבי אלעזר בן עזריה לפני חכמים. darash
Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah lifnei chachamim. So we have the following issue
about the daughter's right to be supported and the fact that the
sons are inherit the mother's כתובה, ketubah, right, the בנין דכרין. benin
dichrin. So those two תנאי כתובה, tenai ketubah, so the mother brings
in her dowry, that goes only to her children, not to the
other children before the estate is divided. And the daughters are supported
by the estate. And the גמרא Gemara says and the משנה Mishnah
says the same way the sons inherit their mother's dowry after the
father dies, the daughters are also only legally entitled to be supported
by the estate after the father dies. Okay, so top of נ"ב
עמוד ב'. nun-bet amud bet. יתיב רב יוסף קמיה דרב המנונא. yasiv
Rav Yosef kamei de-Rav Hamnuna. רב יוסף Rav Yosef was sitting in
front of רב המנונא. Rav Hamnuna. יתיב רב המנונא וקאמר. yasiv Rav
Hamnuna ve-ka-amar. רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna was sitting and saying. כשם שאין
הבנים יורשים אלא מן הקרקע, keshem she-ein ha-banim yorshim ela min ha-karka,
the same way the sons only inherit their portion from the land,
okay, כך אין הבנות ניזונות אלא מן הקרקע. kach ein ha-banot nizonot
ela min ha-karka. Similarly the daughters will only be supported if there
is land in the estate that they can you know that they
can be supported off of. They have a lien, it's like a
debt on the land that's part of the estate. But if there
is no land in the estate, then you will not use the
chattel to pay for their for their מזונות. mezonot. So the גמרא
Gemara says אבשו לה כולי עלמא. avshu lei kulei alma. Everybody yelled,
like there was an uproar. דשביק ארעא הוא דירתי ליה בני? de-shavik
ara hu de-yarti lei benei? What do you mean that only the
same way the kids inherit only if there's land? Somebody who has
land, only then his kids inherit? דלא שביק ארעא לא ירתי בני?
de-lo shavik ara lo yarti benei? If somebody leaves a million dollars
in a bank account, his sons don't inherit? What do you mean,
the same way the only the sons inherit when there's land, the
daughters are fed only when there's land? The sons inherit when there
isn't land, the sons inherit everything. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
ליה רב יוסף, amar lei Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said to him ודילמא כתובת בנין דכרין קאמר מר. ve-dilma ketubat benin
dichrin ka-amar mar. When you say the sons only inherit when there's
land, presumably he says you didn't mean that they only really are
heirs to their father's property if it's landed property. What you meant
was the special inheritance of כתובת בנין דכרין, ketubat benin dichrin, right?
Again, remember, the wife brings in a dowry like I said before
and that money, the value of that dowry, the children, her sons
have rights to before the whole estate is divided amongst the other
sons. That's a lien against the estate. She brought in ten thousand
dollars in dowry. Her sons have a lien against the estate for
ten thousand dollars that they can take out of the estate before
the estate is divided amongst the other sons. That's a lien against
the estate and therefore it only is valid if there is land
because the liens are lien is only on land. So the sons
get their special כתובה ketubah of their money, the dowry back from
their that their mother brought in only if there is land. The
other the rest of the estate is even if it's completely liquid
assets is divided amongst all the kids. But if they want their
rights to what their mother brought in in the dowry, they can
only get that if they have a lien against real estate. And
the same way that's true for the sons, also when the daughters
want to get fed, that's also seen as a type of of
a debt against the estate and only exists if there's actually real
estate. Let me just read it. אמר ליה. amar lei. So he
said back to him מר דגברא רבא הוא, mar de-gavra rabba hu,
you, you're a big תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, so ידעת מאי קאמינא,
yadata mai ka-amina, you understood what I was saying. That's exactly what
I was saying. I was saying that they only get it based
that the sons get their mother's dowry if there's real estate and
the daughters get fed if there's real estate. Let's just read a
little bit more. So אמר רב חייא בר יוסף amar Rav Hiyya
bar Yosef רב זן מחיטי דעליה. Rav zan mi-chitei de-aliya. When רב
Rav had to feed the daughters from the estate, he fed them
even from the grain that was up in the attic. Which basically
means even if there wasn't real estate. Although we've just said the
daughters will only be provided for if there's real estate that they
have a lien against, similar to what we were discussing before about
how do you deal with the legal rights but then the real
needs of the kids. Like so before we talked about like shaming
a person to feed his kids while he was alive. Here, although
technically they only have a right against the estate if there's land,
רב Rav made sure that they were fed even if there was
not land, even from the wheat in the attic. And let's just
read one more line here the גמרא, Gemara, איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu,
פרנסה הויא. parnasa haviya. You know what, let's just end here. It's
8:30. So we will pick up with this and seeing how does
it really develop, is it limited to case of real estate or
not when we continue tomorrow. All right, so I have to pay
off as he...